[Music]
published time the 28th of May 2018 1625
we like to believe and we want other
countries to believe the u.s. is a
shining beacon for human rights civil
rights and civil liberties simply not
true
whistleblower John Kiriakou told artis
on contact host Chris Hedges hedges
discussed the CIA and torture with
whistleblower and former CIA analyst and
case officer John Kiriakou John Kiriakou
is the first u.s. government official to
confirm in December of 2007 that the CIA
was using torture he was charged with
disclosing classified information to
journalists convicted sentenced and
served 30 months in a high-security
Federal Correctional Facility in
Pennsylvania John is currently involved
in prison reform the decision to approve
Trump nominee Gina Haspel as head of the
Central Intelligence Agency raises
serious questions about the rule of law
Haspel is alleged to have been the chief
of a CIA black site in Thailand where
torture occurred and involved with the
destruction of videotapes that recorded
some of the torture of al-qaeda suspects
captured during the Bush administration
[Music]
read more Chris Hedges I want to talk
about torture as somebody who covered
the war in El Salvador
I covered al Qaeda out of Paris for the
New York Times was in the former
Yugoslavia I've been around torture most
of my career and I think what many
people don't understand is that you
torture when your intelligence system
doesn't work a functioning intelligence
system doesn't need to torture what we
saw and you were inside the CIA at the
time was this desire to create a
narrative out of the Bush White House
particularly out of Dick Cheney's office
that Iraq and al-qaeda were somehow
linked so they were seeking to confirm
their own narrative
and my assumption I want you to address
this is that the desperate act of
torture was because that narrative which
turned out to be false was not being
confirmed John Kiriakou I think that's
exactly right and remember that on
September 12 2001 Richard Perle went to
the White House to say we have to attack
Iraq what we saw during those years
especially coming from the office of the
vice president was an effort to come to
a policy conclusion and then to
cherry-pick the intelligence to support
that conclusion hello there was no
intelligence that Iraq was involved in
al-qaeda because they weren't and there
was no reason to attack Iraq at all ch I
was in Paris after 9/11 working with
French intelligence and French
intelligence officials told me that the
CIA had no human assets inside of
al-qaeda none JK that was true and we
saw that in the 9/11 Commission report
this was a complete and total
intelligence failure not just because
the CIA failed to do its job by
recruiting spies to steal those secrets
but also because the relationship with
the FBI was so acrimonious so poor that
there was literally no cooperation
between the CIA and the FBI even if the
FBI had had sources inside outside more
access sources here in the u.s. to
al-qaeda overseas they weren't sharing
it with the CIA CH when I was working
with French intelligence the French
argued that the all of the al-qaeda
attacks that they were able to port were
thwarted by having human assets inside
of the organization
[Music]
that's how they stopped the planned
attack on the Paris embassy that's how
they stopped the planes being flown into
the Eiffel Tower is that correct
j/k that is absolutely correct
[Music]
you can only truly get inside the mind
of a terrorist if you've recruited
somebody next to him you can spend
billions of dollars on electronics you
can give billions of dollars to NSA if
you don't have a human source you're not
going to get the full story read more CH
I want to talk about the nature of
torture because when you've torture it
empowers a certain type of individual
there were 14 people who were asked to
go into what they called enhanced
interrogation just a nice euphemism for
torture and you were the only one of the
14 who refused but if caters to a
particular type of individual as well
being one explained to me who those
people are
[Music]
j/k a CIA psychiatrist once told me that
the CIA actively seeks to hire people
who have sociopathic tendencies not
sociopaths
because sociopaths have no conscience
they easily pass a polygraph but they
are impossible to control people who
have sociopathic tendencies have a
conscience but are happy to operate in
moral and legal gray areas but it's
impossible to keep sociopaths out
[Music]
and it is because they don't have a
conscience
[Music]
just like in corporate America it is
those sociopaths that rise to the top
levels of leadership that is exactly
what we've seen at the CIA when Gina
Haspel was testifying before the
Intelligence Committee she was lauded
for her spine of Steel but she didn't
have the spine necessary to stand up and
say no this is wrong you know this is
illegal unethical or immoral chy is
torturing counterproductive to American
national interests
j/k torture and the torture program are
the greatest recruiting mechanisms for
our enemies it galvanizes people
overseas I'm going to make an analogy in
comparison to the drone program I've
been responsible for the capture and
interrogation of dozens of al-qaeda
fighters none of them at least that the
fighter level had any specific problem
with the US until we started bombing
their villages and killing their family
members and so they joined the fight the
same is true about torture I think it is
a terribly corrosive policy it eats away
at our humanity I say all the time we
like to believe in we want other
countries to believe that we are this
shining beacon for human rights and
civil rights and civil liberties and
it's just simply not true you know every
year the State Department writes the
Human Rights report on every country in
the world with which we have diplomatic
relations you've got a State Department
officer going into let's say a mastery
of Interior and saying look you can't
torture these people you can't arrest
14-year olds you can't do this and that
and the other thing and then an hour
later CIA officer walks into the same
office and says don't pay any attention
to the State Department guy we want you
there are some things that we ought not
to do no matter what the cost and
torture is one of those things watch the
full episode here think your friends
would be interested share this story
[Music]